Washburne, E. B. (Elihu Benjamin), 1816-1887, collector. E. B. Washburne autograph collection, 1766-1888 (MS Am 1583): Guide.
E. B. Washburne autograph collection,
1766-1888.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
MS Am 1583
Washburne, E. B. (Elihu Benjamin), 1816-1887, collector.
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Autographs of American and French historical figures collected by American politician and diplomat Elihu Benjamin Washburne.
Recataloged from X5.13F*. Gift of Mrs. Mary Washburne Fowler, and grandchildren Clarke, Gratiot, Hempstead, and Annette, in memory of Hon. Elihu B. Washburne; received: 1927 December 29.
There are no restrictions on physical access to this material. Collection is open for research.
Washburne was an American politician and diplomat.
Arranged alphabetically by author.
Contains autographs letters from various American and French historical figures, including John Adams, John Quincy Adams, John Hancock, Pierre Menard, Pierre François Tissot, and George Washington. Also includes a letter from the Marquis de Lafayette to Thomas Jefferson and a letter from Thomas Jefferson to Ben Franklin, as well as documents concerning the French Revolution and the Paris Commune, among other items.
- Adams, John, pres.U.S., 1735-1826. A.L.s. to Oliver Ellsworth; Quincy, 22 Sep 1799., (1); 1s. (2p.)
- Adams, John Quincy, pres.U.S., 1767-1848. A.L.s. to Joseph Lancaster; Washington, 24 Jan 1824., (2); 1s.(1p.)
- Adams, Samuel, 1722-1803. A.L.s. to Horatio Gates; Boston, 25 Aug 1779., (3); 1s.(1p.)
- Arnold, Benedict, 1741-1801. A.L.s. to John Imlay; Philadelphia, 10 Jul 1778., (4); 1s.(2p.)
- Astor, John Jacob, 1763-1848. A.L.s. to Messrs. Berthold, Chouteau and Pratte; New York, 12 May 1822., (5); 1s.(1p.)
- Astor, William Backhouse, 1792-1875. A.L.s. to Ramsay Crooks; New York, 5 Mar 1822., (6); 1s.(1p.)
- Bazaine, Achille François, 1811-1888, A.L.s. to [Comte Jean Isidore] Harispe; Miranda de Ebro, 9 Jan 1837., (7); 1s.(4p.) Partly in cipher.
- Bazaine, Achille François, 1811-1888. A.L.s. to Elihu Benjamin Washburne; Madrid, 13 Aug 1880., (8); On verso of photograph of Bazaine.
- Boissy d'Anglas, François Antoine, comte de, 1756-1826. A.L.s. to []; Paris, 25 Feb 1821., (9); 1s.(4p.)
- Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836. A.L.s. to Thomas Tayler; New York, 9 Jul 1802., (10); 1s.(1p.)
- Castellane, Pierre, comte de. A.L.s. to [Comte Jean Isidore] Harispe; Perpignan, 17 Aug 1838., (11); 1s.(1p.)
- Caumont, Arcisse de, 1802-1873. A.L.s. to []; [n.p.,n.d.], (12); 1s.(2p.)
- Clinton, DeWitt, 1769-1828, A.L.s. to Micah Sterling; Albany, 21 Dec 1821., (14); 1s.(1p.)
- Clay, Henry, 1777-1852. A.L.s. to Samuel Smith; Washington, 26 Oct 1826., (13); 1s.(1p.)
- Clinton, DeWitt, 1769-1828. A.L. (3d person) to O. Henry; Albany, 14 Mar 1826., (15); 1s.(1p.)
- Clinton, George, 1739-1812. A.L.s. to [the Senate]; Albany, 8 Jul 1789., (16); 1s.(1p.)
  27 Dec 1927
- Clinton, James, 1733-1812. A.L.s. to [Mrs Clinton]; Fredricks Burgh, 30 Sep 1778., (17); 1s.(2p.)
- Colden, Cadwallader, 1688-1776. A.L.s. to Sir William Johnson; Springhill, 10 Apr 1766., (18); 1s.(3p.)
- Condorcet, Marie Jean Antoine Nicolas Caritat, marquis de, 1743-1794. A.L.s. to [Chrétien Guillaume de Lamoignon de Malesherbes]; [n.p.,n.d.], (19); 1s.(2p.)
- Daunou, Pierre Claude François, 1761-1840. A.L.s. to [Etienne Maurice,] comte Gérard; Paris, 17 Mar 1839., (20); 1s.(1p.)
- Daunou, Pierre Claude François, 1761-1840. A.L.s. to []; [n.p.] 30 Sep 1831., (21); 1s.(1p.)
- David, Jacques Louis, 1748-1825. A.D.s.; Paris, 27 Sep 1775., (22); 1s.(1p.) A receipt.
- De Bry, Jean, 1760-1834. A.L.s. to []; Paris, 15 Feb 1832., (23); 1s.(3p.)
  27 Dec 1927.
- Dubois de Crancé, Edmond Louis Alexis, 1747-1814. A.L.s. to [citoyens directeurs]; Paris, [13 Mar 1797], (24); 1s.(2p.)
- Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790. A.L.s. to Messrs. Robert S. Jones,; Samuel Rhoads and Josiah Hewes; London, 22 Aug 1772., (25); 1s.(1p.)
- French revolutionary documents., (26); 44 pieces.
- Miscellaneous French documents., (27); 13 pieces.
- Goujon, Alexandre, 1766-1795. A.L.s. to [administrators, district of Corbeil]; Versailles, 21 Oct 1792., (28); 1s.(1p.)
- Goujon, Alexandre, 1766-1795. A.L.s. to [Pierre François] Tissot; Versailles, 11 Jun [1794], (29); 1s.(2p.)
- Goujon, Alexandre, 1766-1795. MS.L.s. to [administrators, district of Mantes]; Versailles, 18 Jun 1793., (30); 1s.(2p.)
- Hancock, John, 1731-1793. MS.L.s. to Samuel Holten; Boston, 16 Mar 1785., (32); 1s. (1p.)
- Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804. A.L.s. to Jonathan Dayton; Philadelphia, 13 Aug 1792., (31); 1s.(2p.)
- Harispe, Jean Isidore, comte, 1768-1855. A.L.s. to []; Maulion, 11 Sep 1837., (33); 1s.(2p.)
- Harrison, William Henry, pres. U.S., 1773-1841. A.L.s. to J. C. Hill; North Bend, 2 Jan 1833., (34); 1s.(1p.)
- Healy, George Peter Alexander, 1813-1894. A.L.s. to Elihu Benjamin Washburne; Paris, 17 Nov 1886., (35); 1s.(2p.)
- Huntington, Samuel, 1731-1796. A.L.s. to Roger Sherman; Norwich, 10 Jan 1792., (36); 1s.(1p.)
- Jackson, Andrew, pres. U.S., 1767-1845. A.L.s. to Henry Toland; Hermitage, 12 Sep 1832., (37); 1s.(2p.)
- Jay, John, 1745-1829. MS.L.s. to Abraham Van Vechten; New York, 9 May 1796., (38); 1s.(1p.)
- Jeanbon Saint-André, André Jeanbon, called, 1749-1813. MS.L.s. to [] Vence; Algiers, 17 Apr 1798., (39); 1s.(1p.)
- Jefferson, Thomas, pres.U.S., 1743-1826. A.L.s. to Benjamin Franklin; Paris, 6 Aug 1787., (40); 1s.(1p.)
- Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834. A.L.s. to Thomas Jefferson; La Grange, 25 Feb 1814., (41); 1s.(1p.)
- Lancaster, Joseph, 1778-1838. A.L.s. to [] Feuillet; Philadelphia, 5 Apr 1838., (42); 5s.(9p.)
- Lanjuinais, Jean Denis, 1753-1827. A.L.s. to [] Joubert; Paris, 3 Ayg 1815., (43); 1s.(1p.)
- Latour Maubourg, Rodolphe de Fay, vicomte de, 1787-1853. MS.L.s. to [Comte Jean Isidore] Harispe; Madrid, 14 Apr 1888., (44); 1s.(2p.)
- Laurens, Henry, 1724-1792. A.L.s. to Major General Green; York Town, 28 Apr 1778., (45); 1s.(1p.)
- Livingston, Edward, 1764-1836. A.L.s. to Duke de Broglie; Legation of U. S., 5 Oct 1833., (46); 1s.(1p.)
- Lockroy, Joseph Philippe Simon, called, 1803-1891. A.L.s. to [] Rochambeau; [Paris] 16 Sep 1837., (47); 1s.(3p.)
- Magnier, Brutus. A.L.s. to [Pierre François] Tissot; Perigeux, [11 Apr 1796], (48); 1s.(4p.)
- Marat, Jean Paul, 1743-1793. A.L. (unsigned); to [] Feneau; [n.p.] 15 Feb 1791., (49); 1s.(1p.)
- Menard, Pierre, 1766-1844. A.L.s. to Pierre Chauteau; Kaskaskia, Ill., 13 Dec 1834., (50); 1s.(2p.)
- Metternich-Winneburg, Pauline (Sandor von Szlaviczna) fürstin von, 1836-1921. A.L.s. to []; [Paris, n.d.], (51); 1s.(3p.)
- Mirabeau, André Boniface Louis Riquetti, vicomte de, 1754-1792. Bataille de Fontenoy. A.MS.(unsigned); [n.p., n.d.], (52); 1s.(2p.) Partly in another (unidentified) hand.
- Monroe, James, pres.U.S., 1758-1831. A.L.s. to [George Washington]; Fredricksburg, 15 Feb 1789., (53); 1s.(1p.)
- Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816. MS.L.s. to Abraham Van Vechten; Morrisania, 24 Jan 1810., (54); 1s.(2p.)
- Morris, Robert, 1734-1806. A.L.s. to [Mrs Ferguson]; Philadelphia, 12 Apr 1781., (55); 1s.(1p.)
- Newman, John Henry, cardinal, 1801-1890. A.L.s. to Lord Coleridge; The Oratory, 2 Apr 1880., (56); 1s.(4p.)
- Paris. Commune, 1871-1872. Documents., (57); 11 pieces.
- Prévost-Paradol, Lucien Anatole Prévost, called, 1820-1870. A.L.s. to [Elihu Benjamin] Washburne; [n.p.] 11 [1870], (58); 1s.(1p.)
- Ramsay, David, 1749-1815. A.L.s. to John Witherspoon; Charleston, 28 Feb 1785., (59); 1s.(3p.)
- Rochambeau, Jean Baptiste Donatien de Vimeur, comte de, 1725-1807. A.L.s. to [Comte Dominique Joseph] Garat; Rochambeau [27 Oct 1804 ], (60); 1s.(2p.)
- Romme, Gilbert, 1750-1795. MS.L.s. to [] Cailhava; Paris, 5 May 1792., (61); 1s.(1p.)
- Romme, Gilbert, 1750-1795. A.L. (3d person) to [] Dantic; Paris, 27 May 1790., (62); 1s.(2p.)
- Rouget de Lisle, Joseph, 1760-1836. A.L.s. to [] Perregay; [Paris, 22 Jun 1800], (63); 1s.(2p.)
- Rush, Benjamin, 1745-1813. A.L.s. to David Hosack; Philadelphia, 7 Jun 1809., (64); 1s.(1p.)
- Van Buren, Martin, pres.U.S., 1782-1862. A.L.s. to Major Worthen; Washington, 3 Mar 1822., (65); 1s.(2p.)
- Rutledge, John, 1739-1800. A.L.s. to [.]; [n.p.] 8 Apr 1780., (66); 1s.(1p.)
- Stevens, Benjamin Franklin, 1824-1908. 4 A.L.s. & 1 telegram to [Mrs Elihu Benjamin] Washburne:, (67)
  London, 29 Nov 1870. 1s.(2p.) env.
  Same, 14 Dec 1870. 1s.(1p.) telegram
  Same, 14 Dec 1870. 1s.(2p.)
  Same, 15 Dec 1870. 1s.(2p.) env.
  Same, 8 Feb 1871. 1s.(2p.)
- Tissot, Pierre François, 1768-1854. A.L.s. to [] Richaud; Paris, [30 May 1795], (68); 1s.(4p.)
- Tissot, Pierre François, 1768-1854. [Vie de Alexandre Goujon] A.MS. (unsigned); [n.p.,n.d.], (69); 3s.(10p.)
- U.S. Army. Northern Virginia. MS. agreements. (John Gibbon & 5 others); Appomattox Court House, 10 Apr 1865., (70); 1s.(2p.)
  Re surrender of army of Northern Virginia to U.S. authorities.
- Washburne, Elihu Benjamin, 1816-1887. [Fragment of essay on the administration of President Andrew Johnson] A.MS. (unsigned); [n.p.,n.d.], (71); 1s.(1p.)
- Washington, George, pres.U.S., 1732-1799. [Notes on agriculture] A.MS. (unsigned); [n.p.,n.d.], (72); 1s.(2p.)
  P.11-12 from a notebook, containing abstracts from ch.9-10 of unidentified work.
- Washington, George, pres.U.S., 1732-1799. A.L.s. to Matthew Carey; New York, 22 May 1789., (73); 1s.(1p.)
- Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852. A.L.s. to James McFarlane Mathews; Washington, 22 Feb 1831., (74); 1s.(1p.)
- Wolcott, Oliver, 1726-1797. A.L.s. to Samuel Lyman; Philadelphia, 26 Feb 1781., (75); 1s.(2p.)
  27 Feb 1927
  r.f. X5.13F*
- Ysabeau, Claude Alexandre, 1754-1831. A.L.s. to [Pierre François] Tissot; [n.p.] 5 Jun 1811., (76); 1s.(3p.)